<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.

    </legalnotice>

    <title>Megaco MIB</title>
    <prepared>Micael Karlberg</prepared>
    <responsible>Micael Karlberg</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved>Micael Karlberg</approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2016-12-12</date>
    <rev>%VSN%</rev>
    <file>megaco_mib.xml</file>
  </header>

  <p>The Megaco MIB is not yet standardized and our implementation is based on
    <url href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-megaco-mib-04.txt">
    https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-megaco-mib-04.txt</url>.
    Almost all of the MIB
    cannot easily be implemented by the Megaco application. Instead
    these things are to implemented by a user (of the Megaco
    application).</p>
  <p>So, what part of the MIB is implemented? Basically the relevant
    statistic counters of the <c>MedGwyGatewayStatsEntry</c>.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Statistics Counters</title>
    <p>The implementation of the statistic counters is
      lightweight. That is, the statistic counters are handled
      separately by different entities of the application. For
      example, our two transport modules,
      <seealso marker="megaco_tcp#stats"><c>megaco_tcp</c></seealso> and
      <seealso marker="megaco_udp#stats"><c>megaco_udp</c></seealso>,
      maintain their own counters and the application engine,
      <seealso marker="megaco#stats"><c>megaco</c></seealso>
      maintains its own counters.</p>
    <p>This also means that if users implement their own transport
      services, they need to maintain their own statistics.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Distribution</title>
    <p>Each Megaco application maintains its own set of counters.
      In a large (distributed) MG/MGC it can therefore be necessary to
      collect the statistics from several nodes (each) running the
      Megaco application (only one of them with the transport).</p>
  </section>
</chapter>

